<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Kalevalla.xyz</title>
<description>Articles and blog entries from kalevalla.xyz.</description>
<link>http://kalevalla.xyz</link>

<item>
<title>Remodelling Soon</title>
<pubDate>26 Aug 2025</pub-date>
<description>
    <p>
        I'm thinking I have gathered enough blog posts here that it's probably worthit to switch to a more normal blog format, with an index and separate page for each blog entry; easier to share independently, more structured and whatnot, and I think it's also better for RSS sharing, which I want to implement soon.
    </p>

    <p>
        That implies a bit of work restructuring the site and links, and all that, so it might take me a couple days (or a couple hours, depending on how much my job interferes my hobby). I will say, hosting this on Git and being able ti update evrything with just a git push is awesome; the downside is I cann't have any kind of backend, and I've been learning some PHP, and thinking about setting up some kind of comment box, or something like that.
    </p>
</description>
<link>https://www.kalevalla.xyz/blog/007-remodelling-soon.html</link>
</item>

<item>
<title>Average Ubuntu Enjoyer</title>
<pubDate>20 Aug 2025</pub-date>
<description>
    <p>
        I was just thinking of how there are these Distros that are seen as "for beginners", "too easy", etc, and others that are seen like "real serious Linux". And, well, I've been using Linux as my "daily driver" OS for the past, I think, 5 or 6 years now, more than the average Linux user, and I've come back to Ubuntu. Part of it was that I have a new laptop and I was little afraid to mess it up by installing something exotic and weird. But honestly, I'm enjoying it. I just werks. I have more interesting things to do with my time, than fighting through endless config files in a ton of different programming languages just to display a minimize button on a window or to get the bluetooth to work, or whatever. Don't worry, I'm still learning a ton about Linux, but that's just what I choose to do with my computer; any other user might choose to just play games and log in to Discord and watch YouTube, or do some actual work on something unrelated where they just need a reliable functional OS, but have their own reasons for not using Windows or Mac; and they will choose Ubuntu, Mint or Pop!_OS, because it would be nearly impossible for someone who is non-technical —by this I mean that they have no interest in learning; everybody has the capacity, but not the interest— to accomplish that with any other distro.
    </p>
    <p>And that's fine.</p>
    <p>This is Linux. It's all about the freedom to do what you want with your machine, no more, no less, have the tech work for you and not you working for the tech.</p>
    <p>It's all about the freedom.</p>
</description>
<link>https://www.kalevalla.xyz/blog/006-average-ubuntu-enjoyer.html</link>
</item>

<item>
<title>Give me the adds but keep the trackers</title>
<pubDate>12 Aug 2025</pub-date>
<description>
        <p>
            Some people complain that the internet started going to shit when every page started displaying adds. Well, it couldn't just be free forever, right? There are millions of websites out there that are not really trying to sell you anything, just share information. I do believe that, genuinely, some people just want to share their knowledge and opinions and engage with other like-minded people. But that information still has a value and there is also a cost to broadcast it. I also believe in the right to monetize what you know, so if you know a lot about plants and want to write a website about that, why shouldn't you make some money off of it? 
        </p>
        <p>
            Now, the question is how that money is made. I believe there are ethical ways to make money and there are un-ethical ways to make it; it boils down to a simple principle: consent. 
        </p>
        <p>
            If you are just showing the reader a few adds in your page, the reader can see them and dismiss them and keep on reading the content, and maybe there's a 0.01% chance that they'll click on the add if it's something they are interested in; there is still consent here. It's a small chance, but with enough readers, that small percentage makes the add worth it for the advertiser. As soon as you start adding trackers behind the adds, there is no more consent because the reader doesn't know they are being tracked, or doesn't know to what extent and what is being done with their information. Whether they click on the add or not, it doesn't really matter anymore, value has already been extracted from them. The reader has become the product. Many websites don't even bother having adds now because a) they know that most users have some form of add-block extension; and b) they can get more value out of you by selling your data than on the small chance you'll click on an add.
        </p>
        <p>
            See, the problem is not with the adds themeselves, it's what's behind them. I would much rather open a web page and see a few adds for unrelated things that may or may not be interesting to me and know that that's all there is to it, than to have this feeling that wherever I go, whatever I do, I'm being followed, observerd, every click analyzed, and likely even manipulated by algorithms; that not just the adds, but the content itself if algorithmically designed for maximun engagement. 
        </p>
        <p>
            I miss the old days when you would open a page, see a banner add at the top and another one in the middle; maybe there was a 0.01% chance that the add was for sommething you might actually care about and would click on it and if not you just had the choice to dismiss them and keep reading the content. It seems like even that choice has been taken away from us. Of course, part of the reason we all started using add-blockers was because those adds just became too much. I mean, on a regular page with adds, almost half of the space in the page is add-space. That's too much. But you get my point.
        </p>
</description>
<link>https://www.kalevalla.xyz/blog/005-keep.the.trackers.html</link>
</item>

<item>
<title>Recovering Engagement-o-Holic</title>
<description>

        <p>
            One of these days I'm going to pay for a proper hosting service just so I can set up a php form so that you, my awesome reader, can send me a message and tell me how much my writing means to you.
        </p>
        <p>
            Of course I know that's probably not going to happen, that's my Social Media addicted brain speaking. Who is even reading this any way? It is a little hard to write things that, in many ways, mean a lot lot me, and have zero idea who reads it, zero dopamine reward; there's no "like", no comments, not even a basic web traffic metric. Is this how it used to be before? Am I just talking to the void? "Aaaaaaaaaaaaaaah!"" Is the void looking back? "Hello, Void!". But in another way it's easier to write like nobody's reading, it's liberating.
        </p>
        <p>
            I have a Neocities.org page that I opened about a year and a half ago that I've spent a lot of time at, wrote a buch of things that I'm proud of and in that time managed to get 9 followers. It seems like nothing, but it probably isn't. Besides the engagement (or lack thereof), I am grateful that it gave me a lot of motivation to write more and to search out for other small-web/indie-web pages and communities. It's also just fun. The small engagement features it has &mdash;even if they are very diluted compared to a bigger social network and it certainly helps with the transition&mdash; still make it, in the end, a sort of walled garden, although with a low wooden fence, not a big stone wall... But anyway, bad metaphores apart, I am now completely free from that, now I'm just floating in the wide open sea of the Web, throwing my message in a bottle.
        </p>

</description>
<link>https://www.kalevalla.xyz/blog/004-engagement.html</link>
</item>

<item>
<title>Wake up, it's 1995</title>
<description>
        <p>
            I saw this image last night and the first thing I thought was that I would run to the computer downstairs and get on the Internet and start learning more about it, maybe start learning how to program and create web pages. I was 8 in 1995. I mentioned before that I grew up with some awarenes of what the Internet was, or at least that it existed, but I didn't really care too much about it. Maybe I was just too young, or wasn't geeky enough. Shame on me.
        </p>
        <p>
            The thing is, I've come to the realization that what the small web / old web means to me is more than just than just nostalgia. You see, as an older millenial, I'll be part of the last generation to remember a world without the internet. And more specifically, even though it existed before, I might say that the mass adoption of the Internet hit me at the same time as puberty/adolescence &mdash;what that means exactly I'm not sure, but such a big societal change happening in syncronicity with such an important milestone in life surely has some significance to a person's character.
        </p>
        <p>
            For all that, I've come to the realization that because I had the priviledge to know the Internet as it was in the beginning I feel maybe a little bit of responsibility to preserve at least a part of it, or to try to keep the original spirit alive &mdash;whatever that is exactly, not sure, I'm still discovering it.
        </p>
</description>
<link>https://www.kalevalla.xyz/blog/003-its-1995.html</link>
</item>

<item>
<title>¿Entonces estoy en contra de la IA?</title>
<pubDate>31 Jul 2025</pub-date>
<description>
        <p>
            En una lectura inicial de la entrada anterior, podría parecer a primera vista que estoy en contra de usar programas de inteligencia artificial, que opino que de alguna manera equivale a "hacer trampa". No del todo. Tal vez es necesario matizar eso un poco.
        </p>
        <p>
            Por un lado, sí, estrictamente hablando, lo podríamos llamar "hacer trampa". Porque el hecho objetivo es que cualquier contenido que creaste con IA, tus neuronas se tomaron un descanso, además creo que es muy peligroso, no necesariamente por escenarios tipo Terminator --ese es otro tema aparte--, lo digo simplemente porque a la larga se nos va a atrofiar el cerebro si no lo usamos. 
        </p>
        <p>
            Pero por el otro lado pienso precisamente que si usamos bien estas herramientas, nos abren un universo de posibilidades que de otra forma podía ser inalcanzable para uno. Pero la cuestión crítica es justamente qué es eso de "usarlas bien".
        </p>
        <p>
            Eso puede ser un tanto subjetivo, pero en la base de todo creo que está esta idea: hay que usarlas como herramientas para construir cosas nuevas, pero lo más importante es no dejar de aplicar nuestro pensamiento crítico, asegurarnos de ser nosotros quienes lleven la conversación, que no sea la IA la que al mismo tiempo propone y construye. Y, personalmente, el mejor uso que yo le he enconrtado es para aprender habilidades nuevas, y eso a veces también incluye construir algo desde cero, casi completamente guiado por la IA, pero ahí también la clave está en mantener la conversación en el punto crítico donde la IA me está proponiendo cosas apenas un poco fuera de mi alcance, en el "umbral de aprendizaje" correcto: no tan abajo que no aprenda nada nuevo, pero tampoco tan elevado que no entienda nada de lo que está pasando.
        </p>

</description>
<link>https://www.kalevalla.xyz/blog/002-contra-IA.html</link>
</item>

<item>
<title>Is the Internet dead?</title>
<pubDate>29 Jul 2025</pub-date>
<description>
        <p>
            Have you heard of "the dead Internet theory"? The basic argument is that now, or eventually, most of the content circulating in the  Internet is generated by AI or bots, and not only that, but even most of the supposed engagement is also bots just interacting with each other.
        </p>
        <p>
            There are many aspects to it, and it can be easily misunderstood. But here's just a random thought about it all:
        </p>
        <p>
            Just because a lot of the content you read or watch in social media is generated using AI LLM's or image generators, does that mean that the Internet is dead?
        </p>
        <p>
            After all, there is still someone using their creativity to prompt the AI, right?
        </p>
        <p>
            Well, sometimes. You can just as easily prompt ChatGPT with something like "Write the next viral Twitter thread that will get me all the engagement". And it'll come up with something inflamatory and controversial without you even having to decide on the general topic. You could ask it to write about something more specific, like "write a thread about climate change considering the findings of doctor such and such, defending the argument that it's mostly a scam." It's based on your idea, sure, but the choice of words, the disecting and structuring of the particular points within the subject, are not, not really, as much as you try to prompt engineer the text.
        </p>
        <p>
            The crafting of ideas matters.
        </p>
        <p>
            So yeah, maybe, the Internet is dead and all of us here at the small web are basically just the post-mortem knee jerking of the cadaver.
        </p>

</description>
<link>https://www.kalevalla.xyz/blog/001-is-the-internet-dead.html</link>
</item>

<item>
<title>The Free Web - a manifesto</title>
<description>Web Renaissance, Web Revival, Small-Web, Retro Web, Indie Web, Personal Web, Web0, Web 3.0... What's this all about anyway?</description>
<link>https://www.kalevalla.xyz/the-free-web.html</link>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>